D.C. Federation of Civic Associations 027
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
D.C. Federation of Civic Associations Records
1960-1979
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
D.C. Federation of Civic Associations
027
6.5 Linear feet
16 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Federation Awards, 1963-1984 (1.25 linear ft.) Series contains certificates, programs, and other ephemeral items related to awards given or received by the Federation. Series 2: Topics, 1960-1979 (2.75 linear ft.) This series contains correspondence, clippings, committee reports, memoranda, and financial materials, which document the activities of the Federation. The bulk of the papers are from the 1970s and cover issues and activities such as the Federation's Black Tie Ball, consumer protection, city planning, civil defense the lottery, cultural arts, and home rule. Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic. Series 3: Newsletters, 1964-1979 (1 linear ft.) The series contains newsletters of local civic associations, which are members of the Federation. It also includes the Federation's newsletter. Member newsletters represented include those for Brightwood, Capitol View, and Southeast, to name a few. The folders are arranged alphabetically with the Federation's newsletters appearing first. Series 4: Interfederation and National Business, 1967-1978 (.25 linear ft.) The series consists of the Interfederation constitution, minutes of Interfederation meetings, and materials regarding the National Association of Neighborhoods. Series 5: Meeting Minutes, 1965-1978 (1.25 linear ft.) The series contains meeting minutes, both hand and typewritten for Federation meetings.
Biographical / Historical
The D.C. Federation of Civic Associations (DCFCA) was founded in 1921 to bring together D.C. disparate civic associations under one action oriented organization. In addition to working on common citywide and regional concerns, DCFCA also hosts an Annual Awards Luncheon to showcase the hard work of delegates to the Federation and raise funds for operations and the scholarship program. The luncheon was started in 1930 and awards the George H. Richardson Civil Rights Award and scholarships to high school students.
Custodial History
The papers were donated in 1986 to the Library by Joseph Carter, the DCFCA's President at the time.
Scope and Contents
The records include the D.C. Federation of Civic Associations' (DCFCA) constitution, meeting minutes, and newsletters from member civic associations. It also contains correspondence, reports, clippings, programs, invitations, flyers, legislative materials, handwritten notes, and other records documenting the activities of DCFCA.
Associations, institutions, etc; Neighborhoods; Community development, Urban; Correspondence; Minutes (Records); Organizational Records; Newsletters; African Americans; Civic leaders
- Series 1: Federation Awards, 1963-1984
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains program books, financial materials, correspondence, award applications, address lists, and invitations for annual awards presented to individual civic leaders in Washington, D.C. A few select awards were sponsored by local businesses and civic organizations, including the Evening Star Award, the NAACP Trophy, and a Safeway Scholarship to a local student. The majority of the Awards were given to 'grassroots honorees," from the Federation to citizens working in a variety ways for civic improvement in the District. The folders are arranged chronologically.
  - Federation Awards, 1963-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Federation Awards, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Federation Awards, 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series 2: Topics, 1960-1979
  This series contains correspondence, clippings, committee reports, memoranda, and financial materials, which document the activities of the federation. The bulk of the papers are from the 1970s and cover issues and activities such as the Federation's Black Tie Ball, consumer protection, city planning, civil defense the lottery, cultural arts, and home rule. Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Announcements, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Announcements, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Announcements, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Black Tie Ball, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Black Tie Ball, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Black Tie Ball, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - City Planning documents, 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - City Planning documents, 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Civic Responsibility Week, 1965-1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Civil Protection Committee, 1967-1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Civil Protection Committee, 1967-1979 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Civil Protection Committee, 1967-1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Consumer protection committee documents, 1969-1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Cultural Arts Committee, 1967-1973 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Cultural Arts Committee, 1967-1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Cultural Arts/Scholarship fundraiser project, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Economic Development Committee, 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Economic Development Committee, 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Education Committee, 1973-1979 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Education Committee, 1973-1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Endorsement Policy, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Environmental Committee, 1972-1979 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Annual Father Day's celebration, 1977-1984 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Financial records, 1960-1964 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Financial records, 1960-1964 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Financial records, 1960-1964 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Financial records, 1960-1964 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Financial records, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Financial records, 1975-1979 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Financial records, 1975-1979 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Financial records, 1975-1979 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Financial records, 1975-1979 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Honorary Life members, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Lottery, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Meeting attendance records, 1970-1978 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Membership orientation, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Membership orientation, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Membership orientation, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Membership orientation, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Mothers Day program, 1972-1979 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Mothers Day program, 1972-1979 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Mothers Day program, 1972-1979 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Mothers Day program, 1972-1979 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Mothers Day program, 1972-1979 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Mothers Day program, 1972-1979 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Mothers Day program, 1972-1979 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Mothers Day program, 1972-1979 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - News Media Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - New Media, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - President's papers, 1965-1979 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - President's testimonial for B. Alexander, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Public utilities issues, 1970-1979 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Recreation, 1972-1979 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Recreation, 1972-1979 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Reference materials, 1966-1971 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Reference materials, 1966-1971 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Reference materials, 1966-1971 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Reference Materials, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Rosters, 1965-1979 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Rosters, 1965-1979 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Rosters, 1965-1979 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Rosters, 1965-1979 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Salute to Seniors, 1968-1979 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Sanitation Committee, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Speakers Bureau Project, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Treasurers Reports, 1975-1985 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Transportation, 1969-1979 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Urban Development Committee, 1969-1973 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Zoning, 1966-1972 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Series 3: Newsletters, 1964-1979
  The series contains newsletters of local civic associations, which are members of the Federation. It also includes the Federation's newsletter. Member newsletters represented include those for Brightwood, Capitol View, and Southeast, to name a few. The folders are arranged alphabetically with the Federation's newsletters appearing first.
  - Newsletters, 1966-1972 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters, 1973-1979 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Brightwood Newsletters, 1972-1977 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Burleith Newsletters, 1973-1979 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Capitol View Newsletters, 1970-1984 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Capitol View Newsletters, 1970-1984 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Capitol View Newsletters, 1970-1984 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - North Michigan Park Newsletters, 1972-1979 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Public Interest Community News, 1976-1979 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Southeast Civic Association, 1964-1974 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Southeast Civic Association, 1964-1974 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Southeast Civic Association, 1964-1974 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Southwester Newsletter, 1976-1978 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Series 4: Interfederation and National Business, 1967-1978
  The series consists of the Interfederation constitution, minutes of Interfederation meetings, and materials regarding the National Association of Neighborhoods.
  - Interfederation Council Constitution, 1967, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Interfederation Council meeting minutes, 1969-1974 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - National Association of Neighborhoods, 1977-1978 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Series 5: Meeting Minutes, 1965-1978
  The series contains meeting minutes, both hand and typewritten for Association meetings.
  - Meeting minutes, 1965-1970 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Meeting minutes, 1965-1970 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Meeting minutes, 1965-1970 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Meeting minutes, 1965-1970 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Meeting minutes, 1965-1970 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Meeting minutes, 1965-1970 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Meeting minutes, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Meeting minutes, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Meeting minutes, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Meeting minutes, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Meeting minutes, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Meeting minutes, 1971-1972 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Meeting minutes, 1973-1977 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Meeting minutes, 1973-1977 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Meeting minutes, 1973-1977 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Meeting minutes, 1973-1977 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee and Delegate Assembly, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1978-1979 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1978-1979 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1978-1979 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1978-1979 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1978-1979 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1978-1979 (Box 16, Folder 6)